[Music]
So this morning I want to talk about
uh overcoming
the man within you.
Overcoming the man within you. Uh I know
that there are women in the house. You
are welcome to listen in uh as we talk
uh to men and fellowship with men. Uh
this morning I understand even yesterday
you are online. So you you you already
heard some things that we were
whispering to each other. Uh but you're
welcome. The word of God is available
and he makes it uh relevant to each and
every one of us irrespective of who you
are. So overcoming the man within you,
who is this man within us that we need
to overcome?
Uh I want to propose that that man is
called the human ego.
Ego not eagle you know ego eg o
uh ego especially in the men uh is a
significant factor but ego is not just
in the men is actually in all of us as
human beings. uh one of the things that
distinguishes us as human beings from
other of God's creation
is what is called the ego.
Uh ego is that trait in us as human
beings that enables us to be
self-conscious.
Uh ego is the individual perception or
experience of oneself.
If you did not have ego, you would not
be conscious of yourself. You would not
be selfaware.
That's why animals who do not have this
uh particular trait uh are not
self-conscious. They can do anything
anywhere. Uh they don't care what you
think about them. They just live their
lives uh because that's how God created
them. They don't think. But the human
being because we have this thing called
ego in us. We have a sense of
self-consciousness
and it is that self-consciousness
that helps us to do certain things and
not to do certain things. Ego is an
extremely important trait in every human
being. It enable us to behave ourselves
with a sense of dignity and decorum. So
when you see people who act anyhow howy,
speak anyh howy, do things anyh how you
know that their ego is very low uh
because they are not conscious of
themselves. They are not conscious of
their environment and therefore they can
do anything. But those of us who have
our ego at the right level, uh it helps
us in several things. I want to propose
to us that even this morning as you
stood at your wardrobe considering what
you might wear to come to church, your
ego played a role in it. Uh so um
especially for us who those of us who
are ladies in the house, you know, you
can stand at your wardrobe full of
clothes and then you say I have nothing
to wear.
You're wondering what are all these for
is because you are saying I have nothing
that is appropriate for the occasion for
which I am going. That is your ego
speaking to you and telling you you need
to dress appropriately
so that when you present yourself you
have a sense of dignity and self-ride
even for us as men it is the same uh as
I considered what to wear this morning
that thing played a role how do I want
to present myself to AI Milmani on a
Sunday morning and the choice that was
made is what you see today.
So
this thing called ego is very important.
Uh it helps us in many many ways. Uh so
that we can be able to present ourselves
with a sense of dignity with a sense of
decorum in every place that we find
ourselves. But it is interesting that
this same thing that is an asset to
every human being can also be a great
liability if it is not utilized or
maintained or managed at the right
levels. So
many of us sometimes are driven by our
egos to do some very crazy things and
foolish things even.
In fact, the higher your ego, the more
miserable you are because your life is
likely to be driven by this thing to so
that you do foolish things and crazy
things that you otherwise would not do.
And so as we con focus on men this
morning, uh it is perhaps most fitting
that we consider this man within us.
I want to propose to us that to live as
a redefined man,
to live as a balanced human being, we
must not only overcome but be in control
of our ego so that it is not the one
that is driving us but we are the one
who are making use of the same. And so
we last we want to illustrate this uh
through the study of this one man whose
story has been read for us in the
scriptures from 2 Kings chapter 5
chapter 2 Kings chapter 5. We have read
from verse 1 to 14. Uh the story goes
all the way to chapter 5 verse 27. a
very long story but today we will
reflect only the first 14 verses of that
particular chapter and in this um
particular section we are going to look
at some very unusual happenings in this
uh the life of this man as he uh tries
to navigate life where he found himself.
The first thing I want us to look at is
that this man was an unusual man.
Very unusual man. A highly successful
man.
But a man who in just a few words is
said to have had a very serious disease,
leprosy.
This is a perfect illustration of the
power of the male ego
and it is demonstrated to us through the
life of this man called Naman.
Highly successful. Verse number one
says, "Now Nan was commander of the army
of the king of Aram. He was a great man
in the sight of his master. highly
regarded because through him the Lord
had given victory to Aram. He was a
valiant soldier. And then even the
reader this morning lowered his voice
and said, "But he had leprosy."
In other words, Nemon had everything
that could make him walk on top of the
world.
Let's look at some of the things that
described the life of this man. Number
one was position. Men love positions.
Even if being the chair of the cattle
deep at home.
Positions make men happy, you know. And
this man had position.
His position was not a leader of
something down there. He was the
commander of the king's army.
Naman was part of the king's mafia. He
was in the inner cabinet. He was part of
the security council. He was right there
where the top men of the government sat.
Naman was sitting right there.
He was the minister or CS for internal
security in the land of Aram. This guy
was in a very senior position. But that
was not all. Nan also had prestige.
And I can tell you men love prestige.
sitting at the high table you know where
nobody else is sitting that's where nan
was sitting when he went for a meeting
or a gathering nan was not sitting at
the back there somewhere
he was sitting at the high table men
love that is there any man who does not
like it
some of us even squeeze ourselves where
we do not belong until we are called and
say excuse me Yes, just come come over
here and then you are shown where you
belong. It is a very very embarrassing
experience.
But have you seen a man when they are
brought from the back to the front? They
they walk like this
as they come to to sit where they
believe now they belong because prestige
is part of our lives as men. Nan had it.
The Bible says he was highly regarded by
his master. Nan was a great man in the
sight of the king. Highly regarded by
the king. This is a kind of man who if
you wanted to catch something with the
king, you talked to Nan and your word
went straight without passing through
any other person because the king
regarded him highly. If you needed a job
from state house, Nan was the man to
see. If he attended AIC Milimmani, at
the end of the service, people would be
crowding around him. You know, Dr.
Angusini
you know
there's this contract there's this
tender that I applied for could you that
was nan you know the rest of us we at
the end of the service no one even comes
to greet you
prestige
but nan was a very unique person in the
sense that it was not just position and
prestige
He was also pious.
He had piety.
This guy was a spiritual man.
He believed in God.
Very few people have position and
prestige and still believe in God
genuinely. The Bible tells us that Nan
did not gain his power and prestige
through favors.
He had not schemed his way into state
house.
This man had a CV that read very well
because of the success that had been
given to him by God. Hallelujah.
>> By God, you can be successful
through God's help. And that's who Nan
was because the Bible says through him
the Lord gave victory to Aram. No wonder
the king respected him because when
there was a battle, Nan went out not in
the power of the sword and the spear and
the gun. Nan did not go out because of
the horses.
Nan went out because he believed in God
and God gave him victory. It is very
rare even you know in this country there
are men and women who have been known to
love God. They have been known to fear
God. They have been known you know until
they enter into power.
Then now they forget about God.
Now it is thorax as we say back in at
home in the village.
They are working with the power that
they have and you'll hear them by the
power and authority given to me. They
are not saying by the grace of God. That
one now they have left aside but Nan
conquered battles won all kinds of
battles because of God. a very pious
man. In spite of his prestige, in spite
of his power, he believed in God. And so
God gave him victory and the king
recognize it. But no, that was not all.
Nan also had power.
Power.
The Bible says he was a valiant soldier.
Nan was a very powerful man in every
sense of that word. When Nan went out to
fight battles, he did not just depend on
his soldiers to deliver. He himself
fought and brought victory in the
battlefield. And so his people respected
him because of his proess in the
battlefield. And of course we know
according to what the Bible tells us,
God helped him and gave him victory. And
so became a very valiant military man.
and he was a decorated military soldier
because of the battles that he had won
time and time again. Here therefore was
a truly successful man, a man who walked
the corridors of power and rightfully
enjoyed close association with the king.
Naman was an unusual man. Not many of us
can claim to have all these credentials
that Nan had. Position, prestige, piety,
power, and the list goes on and still
remains sober.
But secondly, we see another unusual
thing about this man. He had an unusual
problem.
He had leprosy.
Unfortunately for Nan, despite his high
position, in spite of the prestige he
enjoyed, in spite of the piety that he
practiced, in spite of the power that he
enjoyed, Nan had an unusual problem. The
Bible puts it simply at the end of verse
one.
But you know that word but negates
everything that has been said.
But Nan had leprosy. In other words, Nan
had the worst kind of disease that any
person would have at this time in
history.
To have leprosy in the days of naman was
not only to have an unccurable disease
but it also came with stigma. In fact,
in some of the societies, people with
leprosy were ostracized. They were
quarantined. Sometimes they were left to
die, especially if the disease had
spread uh over the person. And so, Nan
was not enjoying the life and prestige
that he had. This leprosy was something
that hung over his head. everything
every day. He would sit where people are
sitting but very conscious that he was a
leper and he had this lepous uh disease
upon him.
The sad reality of life is that pain and
suffering
does not respect anybody.
No matter how successful you are, you
will find that there's just this one
thing that eludes you. You can have
position, you can have power, you can
have prestige, you can be highly placed
in society, but deep down within your
heart, deep down within your life, you
find that there's this one thing that
like Nman's leprosy is hanging over your
head.
A child who is rebellious,
a business that is not successful,
a disease that has refused to go
and the list goes on, a wife that is not
listening to you.
You know there are places I don't know
whether you have watched fireproof uh
the movie and this man he had a wife and
he was a fire engine uh a firefighter
the commander on leader of a
firefighting team.
And when he spoke the word everybody ran
and did as he had said.
But when he went home, he spoke the word
and his wife looked at him like, "Where
are you coming from?"
And one time he was so frustrated, he
told his wife, "Do you know where I
work, everybody listens to me. You never
listen to me."
Some of us men are in that situation.
Everybody listens to you except your
children.
your wife.
While the wife is here today, they are
listening to me on your behalf.
So things are going to be changed.
You're going to be a redefined man
in the name of Jesus.
A writer and filmmaker said many years
ago, the rich also cry. There are some
things that money cannot buy. And so Nan
in his all his high position in all his
prestige and power in all his high
connections from uh at the top level of
the country nmon had this one thing
called leprosy.
Paul's had his
the apostle and he called it a thorn in
the flesh and he said I prayed three
times. You know some of us three times
you have not even started praying. But
for Paul to pray three times was too
much because he knew that I talked to
God and it is it happens. So when he
prayed three times he felt that was too
much. And so he said I prayed three
times for God to remove this thorn in
the flesh but it never went
for him. This was the leprosy that was
there. I don't know what yours is. You
have prayed, you have cried, you have
asked God, but it is hangs on uh in your
life not going. So Nmon
an unusual problem.
Nan also experienced an unusual help.
Help from a slave house girl.
The Bible says
in verse number two,
BS from Aram had gone out and taken
captive a young girl from Israel and she
served in Nama served Nammon's wife. Now
she said to her mistress, "If only my
master would see the prophet who is in
Samaria, he would cure him of his
leprosy." Now here was a very
interesting source of help. This young
girl who was a slave girl
looked at the master and say here is a
man who is suffering.
I think he can be helped by the prophet
where I came from. And so he tells the
mother of the house you know
daddy can be helped.
There's there's a man I know who can
help him.
Now think of yourself in that situation
as nmon.
You have power. You have prestige.
You talk to the king face to face, not
through anyone.
You have all that it takes to make you a
man in society. How do you go
to colleagues and friends and say, "My
house girl had advised me.
How? What are you doing with house
girls?
A man of your stature should not be
listening to who? To house girls. You
know,
how do you share with your colleagues?
That is your house girl from Kitui that
has told you there's a camote you can go
and get and can help you with the
problems you are facing. How do you go?
And this is even if you went you don't
tell them where the source of that
information is
because the human ego particularly the
male ego is such that you cannot accept
certain things in your life. How many
men
possibly even sitting here today
will not accept Jesus Christ because
their wives got saved fast
and now they are saying if I get saved
now my friends will say I'm following
the women.
So even as they hear the gospel and they
get convicted they are thinking but I
can't I can't follow my wife. I can't
follow my wife.
How many of us have not driven and got
lost,
you know,
and your wife is telling you I think we
are lost
and you're saying I know what I'm doing
and you drive for 50 kilometers
then you realize indeed you are you are
lost. Then you say what was that you are
saying
that is ego at work.
It can cause you to be lost for 50
kilometers but you won't ask.
This is the man the kind of help that
this man but this man also had an
unusual send off.
When Nan received this advice, he took
it in stride. I like this man because at
this up to this point, he's acting as a
man who has tamed his ego. He listened
to the house girl and decided, let me
give it a try. And so he went to the
king,
his master, to ask for permission. So
the Bible tells us in chapter 5:4,
"Nmon went to his master and told him
what the girl from Israel had said. And
the king replied," by all means go. I
will send a letter to the king of
Israel. So Nmon left taking with him 10
talents of silver, 6,000 shekels of
gold, and 10 sets of clothing. Verse
six, the letter that he took to the king
of Israel read. Here is what the letter
said. With this letter I am sending my
servant Nan to you so that you may cure
him of his leprosy.
In other words, the king
immediately altered the advice of the
girl,
changing it from ascending to the
prophet. And this thing became a GT to G
project,
>> a government to government project
because that's where kings operate.
How do you send a letter to the prophet?
That's lowering yourself. So he sends a
letter to the king
not so that the king can introduce
Nan to the prophet but so that the king
may do what?
Verse six says with this letter I am
sending my servant Nan to you so that
you may cure him of his leprosy. Surely
the chief of the staff
cannot be cured by a prophet.
The chief of staff should be operating
at the king level. So go to the king of
Israel. If they have this thing working
for them, let them apply to you and be
cured.
That is not what the young man, the
young girl had said. Now this thing had
become a G to G government to government
project.
So Nan went off with a copy of this
letter.
And you know this is what happens to us
because of our prestige, because of our
power, because of our position, because
of these things that we enjoy as men.
We are not willing to humble ourselves
and accept that this one I will humble
myself and go and do as I have been
instructed. So you have sent off to go
for the prayer crusade at Divaji Garden.
Is that where we are going next week?
How do I stand in Divaji Garden? Surely.
And then people are going to be passing
by and say, "Hey, that's the chair of
the ESC."
So Mr. Aiko,
I have already told you in advance
and I am sure there are a few of us here
who are thinking likewise. So you want
me to go do what?
Do what?
What are you going to do in divat?
If it's a political rally, I can
understand
those ones we attend.
But our crusade for Jesus
and then people pass by there and see
the chairman clapping hands.
[Laughter]
So instead I will go to the state house
event
because that's where we belong, isn't
it? That's where we belong.
I don't know whether it happens in this
church but I know at least in our church
you know there are these people who are
too big too great
to clap their hands
to dance when people are dancing
in the presence of the Lord. Does it
happen here also? No. Don't say yes.
But these same people
when they are in a political rally
they dance until they go down.
These same people when the traditional
dancers are dancing they cannot keep
sitting on the high seats. They come
down and do what? And dance. But when
they are in church,
what if people see me dancing in church?
What will they think about me? So
their kingship is much more than his
kingship
for them.
That is what was troubling the king of
Aram.
But there was a problem when now this
man took the letter to the king. Oh my,
my my time is over.
The Bible says
the as soon as the king verse seven, as
soon as the king of Israel read the
letter, this is what he said.
He tore his robes and say, am I a god?
Can I kill and bring back to life? Why
does this fellow send someone to me to
be cured of his leprosy?
Look, he's just trying to pick a quarrel
with me. Even the king of Israel, thank
God, knew that this was not in his
domain.
And he knew, no me, I don't give a
people. Why would this person send
someone to me? So, he refused. He was
shocked.
Now let me tell you there are things
that only God can do.
It doesn't matter how high you are.
Humble yourself and come to God and just
say father
this is now beyond any human help.
Please help me my son
Lord is only you can bring him back.
This debt that I'm facing is only you
who can help me. And God who hears and
has mercy on people will hear you. But
if you are going to the king, you know,
you can knock at every door. You you
know CSS, you know PSS, you know even
the president, you know who and who. And
every time you are trying to go to them,
they're saying
right now there's nothing we can do. And
you can go round and round. The only
person you have not knocked at his door
is Jesus Christ.
Let me tell you, the day you knock at
that door, you might find that that
problem is so easy to solve.
There was a time I was looking for uh
something.
And so I called everybody that I knew
who I thought could help me on this
matter. And every person I called, big
guys,
every person I called, they say, "Ah,
now this time, you know, I left that
place." Then I call another say, "Oh no,
the connections that I had have left
that place." Then I I call another one
and said, "Finally, I said, Lord, I know
you are the king who knows that office."
To my big surprise, brothers and
sisters, I was so ashamed of myself.
When I went to this office, right from
the gate, the guard at the gate just saw
me and say, "Bishop, you're here. What
do you want?" And to my embarrassment,
he put me right inside. And I went and I
went. Normally, this process takes about
2 three hours. I was there for 15
minutes sharp. I was done without
knowing anybody.
The God of heaven had orchestrated
everything. I had spent so much time
calling who and who you know I called.
Hey, by the way, you know somebody
there. No, the person I knew left and
then I go somewhere there. No, no, that
one. And nothing doing. But when I took
this matter to the Lord, it was done.
You don't need a G to G.
Just go to the Lord.
And the G with a capital G.
We'll now deal with the other G with a
small G.
>> Hallelujah. And you will be okay.
Hallelujah. You will be fine.
I told my friends here that a pastor,
Pentecostal pastor has five finalists.
So now this is the first one.
As I close,
life has a way of coming to us in very
unusual way.
Do you see the unusual solution that
this man was given? When Elisha, the man
of God, heard that the king of Israel
had torn his robe, he sent this message.
Why have you torn your robes?
Send the man to come to me.
Then he will know there's a prophet in
Israel. So Nmon went to him. Now listen
how Nan goes. So Nmon went with his
horses and chariots and stopped at the
door of Elisha's house. Elisha sent a
messenger to say to him, "Go wash
yourself seven times in the Jordan, and
your flesh will be restored, and you
will be cleansed."
For Nmon, he had humbled himself this
far,
but now this was the limit. His ego
could not go lower than this. He was the
Bible says,
you know, verse 11 says, "Nan went away
angry and said, I thought this man would
surely come out to me and stand and call
on the name of the Lord his God. Wave
his hand over the spot and cure me of my
He even knew how this thing was to be
done.
the pastor was to come out, call him
into his office, wave his hand and say
some things there and the leprosy would
go. So now he's shocked that this man is
telling him to go and wash himself in
the Jordan.
And it is not even the senior pastor who
is doing it. He has sent a messenger.
The chief of general staff
has come to AIC Milimmani and the senior
pastor sends the messenger go and tell
him that that problem of his he should
go to such and such a he does not even
go out to greet
the great man.
You know in our days we worship power.
When power enters in this place we even
reorganize our program.
Isn't it true? I don't know about
we even reorganize our program.
The prophet Elisha did not even come
from where he was sitting.
He say, "Oh, I'm a cua with chariots and
horses. Go and tell him to go and wash
himself, a messenger, not the deputy
senior pastor."
Nan could not take this anymore. He
said,
Amen.
When Nan turned off in rage simply
because of his status
had not been recognized.
But Nan had caring servants and they
went to him and said, "My father,
if the prophet had told you to do some
great thing, would you not have done it?
How much more than when he tells you go
and wash yourself and be cleansed? And
thank God Nan listened. So he went down
and dipped himself in the Jordan seven
times and he was cleansed.
He became like a young boy. Brothers and
sisters, this is my second closing.
Life brings upon us all kinds of things
and there are things that only God can
handle.
I know some of us even our titles if
somebody does not mention that I am
Reverend Dr. Bishop
David Oinde I take great offense.
You know in the good old days the only
people who had titles were doctors,
medical doctors. They were the only ones
who were called doctor so and so. These
days accountants are called CPA. Uh
engineers are called engineer so and so.
You know everybody wants a title and if
it is not mentioned we take great
offense.
In fact, these days I tell people I am
arbishop
because I'm an architect and I'm also a
bishop.
So I am Arkbishop David Oinde. You know
the other day I was in a meeting and
somebody was being introduced CS so and
so I'm thinking which CSD this I don't
know
Kit was certified secretary
and this thing works to soo our
>> our egos.
soothe our egos.
Problems do not know titles.
Challenges do not know positions.
Difficulties do not know where you come
from and what you do. When these things
come upon us, if you are a truly
redefined man or no re
redefined man,
just lower yourself, humble yourself and
come before God. There are solutions in
God's house. There are solutions at
Jesus' feet. It is him who said, "Come
to me all you who are weak and heavy
laden and I will give you rest. Take my
yoke upon you for my yoke is easy and my
burden is light."
When we do this, we find solutions. So
don't worry where the information has
come from. Don't worry who has brought
it. Don't worry what you have been told.
You are a man with leprosy. Accept to be
helped.
Accept to kneel before God. Accept to
cry before God. Humble yourself before
the Lord and let God sort you out
because Jesus Christ said, "I am the
way. I am the truth and I am the life."
And he did not stop there. He said, "No
one comes to the father except through
me." And so, you can run around, you can
do things, you can try that, you can try
that. There are things that money cannot
buy. Only God can help us. And I want to
call upon us this afternoon that we
humble ourselves before God and allow
God to minister to us. God can sort it
out. You dip yourself seven times into
the blood of Jesus Christ and you come
out cleansed and you'll be like a boy.
Hallelujah. Let us pray